Guide to the Henry Haberman Papers, 1945-2002 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Henry Haberman papers 1945-2002 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Haberman, Henry, 1917-2008.
10.0 linear feet Extent: 3000 Items
Henry Haberman (1917-2008) was a New York-based advertising and travel photographer and artist. The Henry Haberman Papers span the years 1945-2002 and include photographs, slides, negatives and print advertisements that document Haberman's work as a photographer in the advertising, fashion and travel fields. Companies represented include Armstrong floors, Bausch & Lomb, B.F. Goodrich, British American Tobacco (Lucky Strike), Cannon, Chatham blankets, Cover Girl (Noxell), DuPont, First National City Bank, General Electric, New York Telephone, Northeast Air, Pepsi, R.J. Reynolds and Shaefer beer. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
RL.00489
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Henry Haberman Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010.
Biographical Note
Henry Haberman was born in 1917, in Brooklyn, New York. He was trained at the New School and the Brooklyn Museum Art School before opening the Habershaw studio in New York City in 1945 with partner Frank Gershaw. Haberman worked as a commercial photographer primarily in advertising until retiring in 1972, and was the recipient of several advertising photography awards. From 1967-1984 Haberman traveled extensively, photographing approximately 40 countries. He became a full-time artist after retiring, showing his paintings in galleries in Mexico. He died in 2008.
Collection Overview
The Henry Haberman Papers span the years 1945-2002 and include photographs, slides, negatives and print advertisements that document Haberman's work as a photographer in the advertising, fashion and travel fields. Companies represented include Armstrong floors, Bausch & Lomb, B.F. Goodrich, British American Tobacco (Lucky Strike), Cannon, Chatham blankets, Cover Girl (Noxell), DuPont, First National City Bank, General Electric, New York Telephone, Northeast Air, Pepsi, R.J. Reynolds and Shaefer beer.
Collection Arrangement
Collection is arranged into four series: Personal Files; Photographs; Print Advertisements; and Slides and Transparencies. Personal Files contain clippings, awards, correspondence and business logo and stationery designs. Photographs include advertising and travel-related photographs, along with examples of some experimental fine-art photography. Print Advertisements include proofs and tear sheets of advertising featuring photography by Haberman. Slides and Transparencies include advertising and travel-related slides, photographic studies of models, and a selection of images of Haberman's paintings. Original folder titles were retained where possible; titles and other descriptive information was transcribed from original envelopes and binders.
Subject Headings
Haberman, Henry, 1917-2008; Armstrong World Industries; Bausch & Lomb, inc.; B.F. Goodrich Company; British American Tobacco Company; Cannon Mills Company; E.I. du Pont de Nemours & Company; First National City Bank (New York); General Electric Company; New York Telephone Company; Northeast Airlines, Inc.; Noxell Corporation; Pepsi-Cola Company; R.J. Reynolds Tobacco Company; Advertising; Advertising -- United States; Advertising -- Photographers; Advertising -- Photographers -- United States; Advertising photography; Advertising photography -- United States; Commercial photography; Commercial photography -- United States; Negatives; Photographs; Slides; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Gene Federico Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company Anthony J. Viola Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company Iconographic Collection
J. Walter Thompson Company John F. Dignam Papers
Pat Finelli Photographs
Robert S. Smith Papers
Sheldon Sosna Papers
T.S. Ferree, Jr. Papers
Detailed Description of Collection
- Personal Files, 1945-2002 and undated
  - Awards, 1954-1955 and undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1964-1974 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1957 (Box 1)
  - Greeting card designs, undated (Box 1)
  - Portrait, undated (Box 1)
  - Slide lists, 2002 and undated (Box 1)
  - Stationery, logos, etc., 1945 and undated (Box 1)
- Photographs, undated
  [Numbers included in photograph descriptions were transcribed from the original containers.]
  - Contact sheets, undated (Box 2)
  - Epcot Center, undated (Box 2)
  - Habershaw promotional sheet, undated (Box 2)
  - Henry Haberman photograph, undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous photographs and contact sheets, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Travel, undated (Box 2)
    [593: Canada, mountains, Guatemala; 592: Africa, Kenya, Dubrovnik (Yugoslavia), France; 159: California, Hawaii, Hong Kong, Japan, San Miguel]
  - Travel, undated (Box 2)
    [594: Paris; 1196: Couple on beach, Lisbon, Paris, Tenerife, Vienna, Athens; 1195: India, Kashmir, Nepal, Bangkok]
  - Travel, undated (Box 2)
    [1197: Copenhagen, London; 1198: Rome, Sicily, Palermo; 1199: France]
  - Travel, undated (Box 2)
    [1200: India, Kashmir, Tivoli Gardens, Rabat, Morocco, Tunis]
  - Travel, undated (Box 2)
    [885-886: Greece; 7001: Hong Kong]
  - Travel, undated (Box 2)
    [7002: Japan; 7003: Paris, Spain, Gibraltar]
  - Travel--Canada, undated (Box 2)
    [1: Niagara Falls, Toronto; 5: Ottowa, Montreal; 6: Ottowa, Montreal, Parliament, Changing of the Guards, St. Anne de Beaupré; 7: Quebec, Jacque Cartier Square, Old Montreal, St. Anne river]
  - Travel--Israel, undated (Box 2)
  - Travel, Washington, D.C., undated (Box 2)
  - Habershaw portfolio, undated (Box 3)
  - Henry Haberman portfolio sampler, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Porfolio of work for New York Telephone, undated (Box 3)
  - Redbook magazine cover image, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Sampler of travel photographs, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Travel photographs, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous large-format photographs, undated (Box 4)
  - Mounted Photographs
    - Advertising and fashion-related, undated (Box 5)
    - Experimental and travel-related, undated (Box 6-8)
  - Scrapbook
    - Photography scrapbook, undated (Box 9)
  - Negatives
    - Miscellaneous negatives, undated (Box 10)
- Print Advertisements, 1957-1967 and undated
  - Armstrong Vinyl Floors, undated (Box 11)
  - Ban, 1958 May (Box 11)
  - Bausch and Lomb, 1967 July (Box 11)
  - BBDO, undated (Box 11)
  - Beaunit, undated (Box 11)
  - B.F. Goodrich, undated (Box 11)
  - Blue Mist Sam (The Man) Taylor and his Orchestra, undated (Box 11)
  - Cannon, undated (Box 11)
  - Carefree, undated (Box 11)
  - Chatham (Esmond and North Star), undated (Box 11)
  - Chrysler Valiant, undated (Box 11)
  - Countess Mara, undated (Box 11)
  - Cover Girl, 1964 (Box 11)
  - Cyanamid, 1962 and undated (Box 11)
  - Dupont (Anti-Freeze, Safety Cushion Glass, Car Wax, Auto Polish, Car Wash), 1957, 1965 (Box 12)
  - Eastern Review, 1966 Oct. (Box 12)
  - First National City, 1965-1966 (Box 12)
  - General Electric, undated [One item relocated to Photographs series, Box 3] (Box 12)
  - The Greater New York Fund, undated (Box 12)
  - Gentlemen's Quarterly (GQ), 1961 Mar.-June (Box 12)
  - Hart Schaffner & Marx, undated (Box 12)
  - Johnson and Siday, undated (Box 12)
  - Keepsake Diamond Rings, undated (Box 12)
  - Lampl, undated (Box 12)
  - Lucky Strike, 1957-1958 (Box 12)
  - Lux, 1958 (Box 12)
  - Maimonides Institute, undated (Box 12)
  - The New York Times, undated (Box 12)
  - Northeast Airlines, 1960-1965 (Box 12)
  - Noxzema, 1960 Aug. (Box 12)
  - Pan-American Coffee Bureau, 1961 Mar.-June (Box 12)
  - Pepsi Cola/Diet Pepsi Cola, undated (Box 12)
  - pHisoHex, undated (Box 12)
  - Radio-Electronics, 1959 Dec. (Box 12)
  - R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Company, 1966 (Box 12)
  - Schaefer Beer, undated (Box 12)
  - Serbin, undated (Box 12)
  - Seventeen, undated (Box 12)
  - Ship'n Shore, undated (Box 12)
  - Surf, undated (Box 12)
  - Tareyton, undated (Box 12)
  - Various Luggage and Fashion Companies (Countdown to Travel!), undated (Box 12)
  - Water, undated (Box 12)
  - Wisk, undated (Box 12)
  - Chatham/Esmond blankets, 1971 and undated (Box 13)
  - Haberman studio advertisement, undated (Box 13)
- Slides and Transparencies, 1961-1993 and undated
  - Advertisements, model editorial, undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Animals, 1976-1985 (Box 14)
  - Antique cars, 1966 (Box 14)
  - Antique show, Mystic, Conn., 1966 (Box 14)
  - Art series, 1983 (Box 14)
  - Carefree, undated (Box 14)
  - Chatham, undated (Box 14)
  - Clown--Circus, undated (Box 14)
  - Color duplicates, undated (Box 14)
  - Europa experimental, undated (Box 14)
  - Family sit--blanket advertisement, undated (Box 14)
  - Future cards, undated (Box 14)
  - Haberman paintings,, 1974-1987, (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - Lucky Strike, New York Times, undated (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous slides, 1962-1986, (5 folders) (Box 15)
  - Models
    - Alita Naughton, 1962 (Box 15)
    - Bianca Benedict, 1963 (Box 15)
    - Carol Ford, 1962 (Box 15)
    - Delores Major, 1966 (Box 15)
    - Dolores Hart, undated (Box 15)
    - Elke Heilman, 1964-1966 (Box 15)
    - Ginny Hulting, 1964 (Box 15)
    - Ginny Hulting-Graulin, 1964 (Box 15)
    - Helaine Carle, Plaza 5, 1961 (Box 15)
    - Helen Williams, 1968 (Box 15)
    - Jenny Asp, 1964 (Box 15)
    - Mary Penn, undated (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous models, 1961 and undated, (1 of 3 folders) (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous models, 1961 and undated (continued), (2-3 of 3 folders) (Box 16)
    - Mona Grant, 1968 (Box 16)
    - Nina Paige, Gill Agency, 1964 (Box 16)
    - Phyliss Newell, 1964 (Box 16)
    - Rose Mary Howard and Bridgette Bauer, Zotos, undated (Box 16)
    - Russ Norris and Grace, Lucky Strike, undated (Box 16)
    - Sally Murdock, undated (Box 16)
    - Shirley Yelm, 1964 (Box 16)
  - Paint A Rainbow (What Makes Sammy Run? Broadway show), circa 1964 (Box 16)
  - Poster--Buck Canell, undated (Box 16)
  - Queen Elizabeth II (cruise ship), 1986 (Box 16)
  - Redbook cover, Sally Murdock and others, undated (Box 16)
  - Room on wheels, BBDO, 1969 (Box 16)
  - Schaefer Beer examples, undated (Box 16)
  - Schiffmacher's office, 1971 (Box 16)
  - Slides of print advertisements, undated (Box 16)
  - Studio Circus, Madison Square Gardens, undated (Box 16)
  - Tareyton, 1966 (Box 16)
  - WWI aircraft, 1966-1967 (Box 16)
  - Travel slides
    - Australia/New Zealand, 1980-1986 (Box 17)
    - Austria, 1969-1986 (Box 17)
    - Barbados, 1971 (Box 17)
    - Belgium, 1968 (Box 17)
    - Burma, 1970 (Box 17)
    - Canada, 1987 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - Canary Islands (including Tenerife and Madeira), 1970-1986 (Box 17)
    - Denmark, 1985-1986 (Box 17)
    - Egypt, 1982-1986 (Box 17)
    - El Salvador, 1973 (Box 17)
    - England, 1968-1985 (Box 17)
    - Europe miscellaneous, undated (Box 17)
    - France, 1968-1988, (4 folders) (Box 18)
    - Greece, 1969-1993 (Box 18)
    - Grenada, 1986 (Box 18)
    - Guatemala, 1973 (Box 18)
    - Haiti, 1986 (Box 18)
    - Hawaii, 1970-1986 (Box 18)
    - Hong Kong, 1970-1986 (Box 18)
    - India, 1970-1986 (Box 18)
    - Indonesia (including Java and Bali), 1980 (Box 18)
    - Iran, 1970 (Box 18)
    - Ireland, 1977 (Box 18)
    - Israel, 1971-1988, (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - Italy, 1968-1986, (4 folders) (Box 19)
    - Jamaica, undated (Box 19)
    - Japan, 1970-1986, (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - Kenya, 1983-1986 (Box 20)
    - Martinique, 1971-1986 (Box 20)
    - Malaysia/Singapore, 1980 (Box 20)
    - Mexico, 1972-1986 (Box 20)
    - Monaco/Morocco, 1968-1970 (Box 20)
    - Nepal, 1970-1986, (2 folders) (Box 20)
    - Netherlands, 1968 (Box 20)
    - New York, N.Y., 1963-1986 (Box 20)
    - Norway, 1968-1983 (Box 20)
    - Panama, undated (Box 20)
    - Peru, 1976 (Box 21)
    - Portugal, 1969-1986 (Box 21)
    - Spain/Gibraltar, 1968-1986, (5 folders) (Box 21)
    - Sweden, 1983 (Box 21)
    - Switzerland, 1970-1986 (Box 21)
    - Taiwan, 1970-1980 (Box 21)
    - Tahiti, 1980 (Box 21)
    - Thailand, 1980-1986 (Box 21)
    - Tunisia, 1970-1986 (Box 22)
    - Turkey, 1970-1982 (Box 22)
    - United States, various cities, 1970-1988 (Box 22)
    - Venezuela, 1976-1980 (Box 22)
    - Virgin Islands, 1965 (Box 22)
    - Washington, D.C., 1981-1986 (Box 22)
    - Yugoslavia, 1968-1969 (Box 22)
  - Large-format transparencies, 1965 and undated
    - Fashion and experimental, undated, (4 folders) (Box 23)
    - Elke Heilman, nudes on location, 1965 (Box 24)
    - Fashion color samples, undated (Box 24)
    - Fashion location tests, undated (Box 24)
    - Old color samples, undated (Box 24)
    - Schaefer Beer color samples, undated (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous transparencies, undated (Box 25)